Arabic: مشعلة أو مشحلة كما ورد اسمها في كتاب ياقوت الحموي
معجم البلدان.
English Translation: Mash'alah, or Mashhalah as its name
appeared in Yaqut al-Hamawi's book, Dictionary of Countries.
Arabic: قرية سورية صغيرة تتبع ناحية شران، منطقة عفرين، ريف
حلب الشمالي.
English Translation: A small Syrian village belonging to the
Sharran sub-district, Afrin region, in the northern
countryside of Aleppo.
Arabic: وقد بنيت فوق مرتفع جبلي، على الجهة الشمالية لوادي
كفر جنة.
English Translation: It was built on a mountain highland, on
the northern side of the Kafr Jannah valley.
Arabic: تبعد عن ناحية شران ثلاثة كيلومترات باتجاه الجنوب
الشرقي، وعن مدينة حلب خمسين كيلومتراً باتجاه الشمال.
English Translation: It is located three kilometers
southeast of the Sharran sub-district, and fifty kilometers
north of the city of Aleppo.
Arabic: يمر شمالها خط سكة الحديد ونفق مشعلة التاريخي.
English Translation: To its north passes the railway line
and the historical Mash'alah tunnel.
Arabic: وإلى الجنوب منها يعبر طريق حلب عفرين إعزاز، وأيضاً
زيارة حنان الشهيرة.
English Translation: To its south crosses the Aleppo-Afrin-
Azaz road, as well as the famous Ziyarat Hanan.
Arabic: وإلى الغرب منها توجد آثار عريقة لسواقي وآبار رومانية
تاريخية، وأيضاً خط سكة الحديد.
English Translation: To its west, there are ancient ruins of
historical Roman water channels and wells, as well as the
railway line.
Arabic: أهلها الأصليين من الأكراد والعرب السوريين.
English Translation: Its original inhabitants are Syrian
Kurds and Arabs.
Arabic: تبلغ مساحة القرية ألفي هكتار، مزروعة بالزيتون
والرمان والحبوب والخضراوات.
English Translation: The area of the village is two thousand
hectares, planted with olives, pomegranates, grains, and
vegetables.
Arabic: يوجد فيها خمسة وعشرون ألف شجرة زيتون.
English Translation: There are twenty-five thousand olive
trees in it.
Arabic: يسكنها حالياً مائتان وخمسون عائلة من سكانها
الأصليين، إضافة إلى عوائل سورية مهجرة قسراً من حمص وحلب
وغيرها.
English Translation: It is currently inhabited by two
hundred and fifty families of its original residents, in
addition to Syrian families forcibly displaced from Homs,
Aleppo, and elsewhere.
Arabic: هاجر قسم من أبنائها إلى أوروبا وتركيا للعمل.
English Translation: A portion of its people migrated to
Europe and Turkey for work.
Arabic: يوجد فيها معصرة للزيتون، ومدرسة ابتدائية وحيدة.
English Translation: It has an olive press and a single
primary school.
Arabic: اشتهرت مشعلة تاريخياً بالرمان والزيتون ونبعة الماء
الموجودة فيها والتي كانت مقصداً سياحياً لأهالي حلب.
English Translation: Mash'alah has historically been famous
for pomegranates, olives, and the water spring located in
it, which was a tourist destination for the people of
Aleppo.
Arabic: مجرى الماء الذي يمر من حدودها الجنوبية الشرقية يصب
في وادي نهر عفرين.
English Translation: The water stream that passes through
its southeastern borders flows into the valley of the Afrin
River.
Arabic: من الناحية التاريخية مشعلة تقع في منطقة جغرافية غنية
بالآثار التاريخية التي تعبر عن كافة مراحل التاريخ التي مرت
على هذه المنطقة.
English Translation: Historically, Mash'alah is located in a
geographical area rich in historical monuments that reflect
all the historical stages this region has gone through.
Arabic: ابتداءً من المرحلة ما قبل الرومانية، ثم الرومانية
فالبيزنطية، وصولاً إلى الفتح العربي الإسلامي وحتى المرحلة
الحالية.
English Translation: Starting from the pre-Roman era, then
the Roman and Byzantine eras, down to the Arab Islamic
conquest and up to the present stage.
Arabic: أيضاً هناك شواهد على الأديان الثلاثة في هذه المنطقة
كما سنشاهد لاحقاً في زيارة حنان.
English Translation: There is also evidence of the three
religions in this region, as we will see later in Ziyarat
Hanan.
Arabic: للحديث عن تاريخ قرية مشعلة يسرنا أن يكون ضيفاً معنا
المختار أحمد رشيد أبو ماهر، العارف بتاريخ مشعلة.
English Translation: To talk about the history of the
village of Mash'alah, we are pleased to have with us as a
guest the Mukhtar Ahmad Rashid Abu Maher, who is
knowledgeable about the history of Mash'alah.
Arabic: الله يعطيك العافية يا مختار.
English Translation: May God give you health, Mukhtar.
Arabic: أهلاً وسهلاً. يا أهلين وسهلين. حياك الله.
English Translation: Welcome. You are very welcome. May God
greet you.
Arabic: هلق أنا لاحظت إنه هون في مغر.
English Translation: Now, I noticed that there are caves
here.
Arabic: وهيدا هون في آثار قديمة.
English Translation: And over here, there are ancient ruins.
Arabic: إي لسواقي مي هي.
English Translation: Yes, these are for water channels.
Arabic: سواقي مي.
English Translation: Water channels.
Arabic: وبير مي هذا.
English Translation: And this is a water well.
Arabic: بير مي شو هاد؟ يعني بير...
English Translation: What kind of water well is this? I mean
a well...
Arabic: هذا مجرى كان هذا، هذا بين الطريقين كان ينحط البوري،
هذا البير، وتعدي المي من تحت الطريق.
English Translation: This was a waterway. Between the two
roads, a pipe would be placed, this well, and the water
would pass under the road.
Arabic: يعني هي قناي؟
English Translation: So this is a canal?
Arabic: إي قناية، إيوا، وتعدي من تحت الطريق.
English Translation: Yes, a canal, exactly, and it passes
under the road.
Arabic: يعني هذا البير لأي مرحلة؟
English Translation: I mean, to which era does this well
belong?
Arabic: بير قديم كتير يعني.
English Translation: It's a very old well, you know.
Arabic: يعني المرحلة الرومانية؟
English Translation: So, the Roman era?
Arabic: يقال إنه المرحلة الرومانية، وهي آثار السواقي هي هون
كمان.
English Translation: It is said to be from the Roman era.
And these are the ruins of the channels here too.
Arabic: هي القناة.
English Translation: This is the canal.
Arabic: أيوا هي كانت هيك كلها هي مجرى مي كانت.
English Translation: Exactly, all of this used to be a
waterway.
Arabic: ومن فترة يعني غير بعيدة، من شغلة أربعين سنة، هي كانت
كلها تشتغل، المياه كان..
English Translation: And not so long ago, about forty years
ago, all of this was working, the water was...
Arabic: هي السواقي كانت تسقي الأراضي أم تسقي الناس؟
English Translation: Did these channels irrigate the lands
or provide water for the people?
Arabic: تسقي الأراضي وتسقي الناس، لأنه هي عبارة عن مياه
ينابيع، مياه نقية جداً يعني.
English Translation: Irrigate the lands and provide water
for the people, because they are spring waters, very pure
waters, you know.
Arabic: منين تجي؟
English Translation: Where does it come from?
Arabic: تجي من كفر جنة.
English Translation: It comes from Kafr Jannah.
Arabic: من كفر جنة اللي صايرة..
English Translation: From Kafr Jannah, which is located...
Arabic: أيوا صايرة شرقنا إيوا.
English Translation: Exactly, located to our east, yes.
Arabic: شرقنا. طيب، خلينا نمشي هيك شوي ننزل باتجاه الطريق
الرئيسي.
English Translation: To our east. Okay, let's walk this way
a bit, going down towards the main road.
Arabic: احكي لي يعني تاريخ هالقرية من إيمتى يبدأ؟ أقدم شيء
في القرية إيمتى يبدأ؟
English Translation: Tell me, I mean, when does the history
of this village begin? When does the oldest thing in the
village date back to?
Arabic: والله تاريخ القرية يعني مثل ما قلت أنت الآثار تدل
على قدم القرية يعني.
English Translation: Well, the history of the village, as
you said, the ruins indicate the antiquity of the village.
Arabic: قدمها التاريخي يعني، هاي المغر بتدل على الإنسان
القديم يعني.
English Translation: Its historical antiquity, I mean. These
caves point to ancient humans, you know.
Arabic: سكان الكهوف يعني، لأنه عبارة في مغر كثيرة هون
بالمنطقة.
English Translation: Cave dwellers, I mean, because there
are many caves here in the area.
Arabic: وكانوا يعني قديماً يحكولنا أجدادنا إنه كانوا فيها
سكان يعني، كانت الناس تسكن فيها يعني.
English Translation: And in the past, our ancestors used to
tell us that there were inhabitants in them, I mean, people
used to live in them.
Arabic: على وعيهم؟
English Translation: In their living memory?
Arabic: لا مو على وعيهم، أجدادهم بيحكولهم إنه هي المغر كانت
مسكونة بالإنسان يعني.
English Translation: No, not in their memory. Their
ancestors would tell them that these caves were inhabited by
humans, I mean.
Arabic: طيب في شيء آثار مبنية، بيوت، كذا، قلاع في القرية
بتعود للمرحلة الرومانية؟
English Translation: Okay, are there any built ruins,
houses, and such, castles in the village dating back to the
Roman era?
Arabic: والله للأسف أغلبها مندثرة يعني، ما بت...
English Translation: Unfortunately, most of them have
disappeared, they don't...
Arabic: بس هالسواقي المي هي، وهي الآبار تبع اللي تنقل المي
من تحت الطريق.
English Translation: Except for these water channels, and
these wells that transport water under the road.
Arabic: هي موجودة، وما تبقى كله مندثر يعني.
English Translation: These are present, but the rest has all
disappeared.
Arabic: طيب الآن السكان الحاليين الموجودين هون، والقرية
الحالية بشكلها الحالي قديش عمرها؟
English Translation: Okay, now the current residents who are
here, and the current village in its current form, how old
is it?
Arabic: والله يعني عمرها بالضبط يعني...
English Translation: Well, its exact age, I mean...
Arabic: يعني ما بنعرف بالضبط، بس يمكن يعني حوالي الخمسمائة
سنة يعني هذول السكان المأكدين يعني.
English Translation: We don't know exactly, but maybe around
five hundred years, I mean, these are the confirmed
inhabitants.
Arabic: احكي لي عن التنويعة السكانية اللي هون.
English Translation: Tell me about the demographic diversity
here.
Arabic: السكان هون من الإخوة الأكراد وفي يعني من الإخوة
العرب كمان.
English Translation: The residents here are of Kurdish
brothers, and there are, I mean, Arab brothers as well.
Arabic: إخوة عرب قديمين صار لهم أكثر من مية سنة كمان،
مستوطنين معنا بالضيعة، وإلهم أملاك وإلهم أرزاق.
English Translation: Old Arab brothers who have been here
for over a hundred years too, settled with us in the
village, and they have properties and livelihoods.
Arabic: ومصاهرة مع أهل الضيعة، يعني وقديمين نحن أهل يعني منا
وفينا.
English Translation: And intermarriages with the people of
the village. I mean, they are old residents; we are family,
they are part of us.
Arabic: يعني الأكراد أقدم من العرب هون؟
English Translation: So the Kurds are older than the Arabs
here?
Arabic: إي الأكراد أقدم من العرب، أيوا.
English Translation: Yes, the Kurds are older than the
Arabs, exactly.
Arabic: بينتموا لأي عشيرة الأكراد؟ منين إجوا؟
English Translation: Which tribe do the Kurds belong to?
Where did they come from?
Arabic: والله هن بشو اسمه...
English Translation: Well, they are from what's it called...
Arabic: أغلب سكان الضيعة نحن بيقولولنا عشيرة الملي خضرآكي.
English Translation: Most of the village's residents, we are
called the Melli Khidraki tribe.
Arabic: أو الشيخ خضر يعني بالعربي اسمه الشيخ خضر.
English Translation: Or Sheikh Khidir, I mean, in Arabic its
name is Sheikh Khidir.
Arabic: بالكردي بيقولوا له الملا خضرآكي، الملا بالكردي يعني
هو الشيخ يعني.
English Translation: In Kurdish, they call him Mulla
Khidraki. Mulla in Kurdish means the Sheikh, you know.
Arabic: يعني نحن بيقولوا، طبعاً مو كل مشعلة، كل عائلات..
English Translation: I mean, they say, of course not all of
Mash'alah, all the families...
Arabic: أنتم شيكيك؟
English Translation: Are you Shikak?
Arabic: إيوا نحن شيكيك، نحن عشيرة شيكيك بيقولولنا أيوا.
English Translation: Yes, we are Shikak, we are called the
Shikak tribe, exactly.
Arabic: طيب. والعرب؟
English Translation: Okay. And the Arabs?
Arabic: والعرب من إخوتنا العجيل.
English Translation: And the Arabs are from our brothers,
Al-Ajeel.
Arabic: منين إجوا؟
English Translation: Where did they come from?
Arabic: إجوا من يعني من المناطق...
English Translation: They came from, I mean, from the
regions...
Arabic: إعزاز هون ولا؟
English Translation: Azaz here, or?
Arabic: هون إعزاز وما إعزاز أيوا.
English Translation: Here, Azaz and its surroundings, yes.
Arabic: احكي لي تاريخياً كيف كانت العلاقة بين الطرفين؟ في
مصاهرة؟
English Translation: Tell me historically, how was the
relationship between the two parties? Is there
intermarriage?
Arabic: العلاقة نحن مثل الإخوة يعني، وعلاقة مصاهرة يعني.
English Translation: Our relationship is like brothers, you
know, and a relationship of intermarriage.
Arabic: يعني متزوجين منا ونحن كمان شو اسمه...
English Translation: I mean, they have married from us, and
we also, what do you call it...
Arabic: عاطينهم وعاطينا يعني، نفس الشيء يعني.
English Translation: We have given them [in marriage] and
they have given us, it's the same thing, you know.
Arabic: في مصالح مشتركة كمان، عمل وشراكات؟
English Translation: Are there shared interests too, work
and partnerships?
Arabic: كل شيء كل شيء، نحن أهل، نحن أهل بمعنى الكلمة يعني.
English Translation: Everything, everything. We are family,
we are family in the true sense of the word.
Arabic: أعراس وعزوات...
English Translation: Weddings and condolences...
Arabic: هالزيتون المزروع هون...
English Translation: These olives planted here...
Arabic: أنا حسب ما فهمت إنه المنطقة كانت غنية كتير في
الرمان، يعني هي أعرق من الباسوطة في الرمان؟
English Translation: As I understand, the area was very rich
in pomegranates. I mean, it's more deeply rooted in
pomegranates than Al-Basouta?
Arabic: إي طبعاً طبعاً. وقت اللي كانت المي موجودة هون...
English Translation: Yes, of course, of course. When water
was available here...
Arabic: يعني كانت كل أرض رمان هون، هي حوالي القرية كلها
بساتين رمان كان يعني.
English Translation: I mean, every piece of land was
pomegranates here. The entire surroundings of the village
were pomegranate orchards.
Arabic: أنا أوعى أنا صغير، هون هالمنطقة هي هلق اللي قاحلة
اللي صورناها...
English Translation: I remember when I was young, this area
right here, which is now barren, that we just filmed...
Arabic: اللي عند الصخور ما صخور، هي كلها كانت مزروعة رمان.
English Translation: Near the rocks and all, all of it was
planted with pomegranates.
Arabic: إيمتى صارت هون زيتون؟
English Translation: When did it become olives here?
Arabic: الزيتون كمان قديم الزيتون ما شلون؟
English Translation: The olives are also old, the olives,
you know?
Arabic: بس كضمن القرية كبساتين كلها كانت رمان.
English Translation: But within the village itself, as
orchards, they were all pomegranates.
Arabic: رمان وجوز ولوز وعنب وما شلون...
English Translation: Pomegranates, walnuts, almonds, grapes,
and you know...
Arabic: مناطق الزيتون كانت خارج القرية.
English Translation: The olive areas were outside the
village.
Arabic: تمام. طيب هلق أنا بعرف إنه في عندكم نبعة مي وفي
عندكم وادي.
English Translation: Great. Well, now I know that you have a
water spring and you have a valley.
Arabic: إي.
English Translation: Yes.
Arabic: وفي زيارة حنان.
English Translation: And there is Ziyarat Hanan.
Arabic: إي.
English Translation: Yes.
Arabic: يعني الوجهة السياحية للقرية وللمنطقة هون.
English Translation: I mean, the tourist destination for the
village and the area here.
Arabic: بدنا نروح برفقتك على المجرى المائي وعلى نبعة المي
وبعدين ننطلق على زيارة حنان.
English Translation: We want to go with you to the waterway
and to the water spring, and then head to Ziyarat Hanan.
Arabic: ماشي.
English Translation: Alright.
Arabic: وعالنفق كمان.
English Translation: And to the tunnel as well.
Arabic: إن شاء الله.
English Translation: God willing.
Arabic: تفضل أستاذ.
English Translation: Please go ahead, sir.
Arabic: حلوة كتير الضيعة بالربيع.
English Translation: The village is very beautiful in the
spring.
Arabic: إي كثير. عنا الضيعة كثير كثير حلوة بالربيع.
English Translation: Yes, very much so. Our village is very,
very beautiful in the spring.
Arabic: هلا نحن رايحين على معمل، كان معمل سياحي.
English Translation: Now we are going to a factory, it used
to be a tourist factory.
Arabic: هلا منطقة النبعات بدنا نروح عليها هي.
English Translation: Now we want to go to the springs area.
Arabic: كانت سابقاً معلم سياحي يعني.
English Translation: It previously used to be a tourist
landmark.
Arabic: إخوتنا الأرمن وإخوتنا من حلب ومن الشام كلهم كانوا
يرتادوا...
English Translation: Our Armenian brothers and our brothers
from Aleppo and from Damascus, all used to frequent...
Arabic: يرتادوا النبع يعني ما شلون، يزوروها يعني.
English Translation: They used to frequent the spring, you
know, visit it.
Arabic: من وين ندخل لهون؟
English Translation: From where do we enter here?
Arabic: بدك تطلع مع الطريق.
English Translation: You have to go up with the road.
Arabic: هي بقايا الرمان اللي كانت...
English Translation: These are the remains of the
pomegranates that were...
Arabic: مشهورة فيها.
English Translation: It was famous for.
Arabic: إي طبعاً طبعاً إيوا.
English Translation: Yes, of course, of course, yes.
Arabic: ما ضل يعني، أكثر شيء صار زيتون و...
English Translation: Nothing is left. Mostly it has become
olives and...
Arabic: والكرْمة، كرمة موجودة يعني بس كرمة بكميات قليلة يعني
مو مثل الأول يعني.
English Translation: And vines. Vines exist, but in small
quantities, not like before.
Arabic: هلق دخلنا الان عالقرية.
English Translation: Now we have entered the village.
Arabic: إي وهلا دخلنا على القرية.
English Translation: Yes, and now we have entered the
village.
Arabic: هذا جامع مبني جديد يعني.
English Translation: This is a newly built mosque, you know.
Arabic: إي طبعاً مبني بتبرعات...
English Translation: Yes, of course, built with donations...
هي هون هلا صرنا في القسم القديم، واضح الطابع القديم.
We are now in the old section, the old character is clear.
أيوة.
Yes.
هي من القديم هون.
This is from the old era here.
هي آثار من القديم.
These are ancient ruins.
هلا بدنا ندخل ع اليسار من هون، باتجاه النبعة.
Now we will go left from here, towards the spring.
باتجاه النبعة؟
Towards the spring?
إي.
Yes.
هي اسمها بالكردي سيكانيير، يعني كان ثلاث نبعات.
Its name in Kurdish is Sêkaniyê, meaning there were three
springs.
نعم.
Yes.
سيكانيير يعني ثلاث نبعات، سابقا كان ثلاث نبعات، بس هلا ما ضل
غير نبعة وحدة.
Sêkaniyê means three springs, previously there were three
springs, but now there is only one left.
بسبب كميتها القليلة يعني؟
Because of its low quantity?
بسبب ندرة الأمطار يعني مثل أولي.
Because of the scarcity of rain compared to before.
لأنه كانت المنطقة أولي مشهورة بالأمطار والثلوج.
Because the region used to be famous for rain and snow.
بس حاليا الأمطار يعني قليلة كتير يعني.
But currently, the rains are very little.
والثلوج كانت على مدار العام مثلا مرتين ثلاثة ينزل ثلج.
And the snow used to fall two or three times throughout the
year.
هلا ما في يعني، ندرة يعني ما في.
Now there isn't any, it's rare, there isn't any.
هي هذا الوادي اللي بتجري منه المياه.
This is the valley where the water flows.
وصلنا الآن للوادي وللنبعات.
We have now reached the valley and the springs.
رح نوقف هون، ونتابع مشي على الأقدام.
We will stop here and continue on foot.
مختار، واضحة المي هون.
Mukhtar, the water is clear here.
إي، هي نبعة هون لا زالت نبعة شغالة.
Yes, there is a spring here that is still running.
هي نبعة شغالة هون.
This spring is running here.
كان في نبعتين كمان، وحدة هنيك ووحدة هنيك.
There were two other springs as well, one there and one
there.
حاليا إذا ما في أمطار موسمية جيدة ما بينبعوا، يعني بيوقفوا.
Currently, if there is no good seasonal rain, they don't
spring, meaning they stop.
بس هي على مدار السنة ما بتنقطع.
But this one does not stop throughout the year.
نمشي باتجاه راس النبعة.
Let's walk towards the source of the spring.
إي تمام.
Yes, alright.
بشكل موازي مع الوادي.
Parallel to the valley.
طبعا الوادي هون بيشتهر بتوت العليق.
Of course, the valley here is famous for blackberries.
التوت البري نحن بنقول له التوت البري، توت العليق.
Wild berries, we call them wild berries, blackberries.
الوادي كله كان مليان توت عليق يعني، ولا زال يعني.
The whole valley was full of blackberries, and it still is.
بس كانت كمياته أولي مضاعفة كتير يعني.
But its quantities in the past were much higher.
هلا هذا الوادي كان على أطرافه في أشجار عالية.
Now, this valley used to have tall trees on its edges.
أشجار عالية، انقصت، في كتير أشجار انقصت يعني من هون.
Tall trees, they were cut down, many trees were cut down
from here.
هذا شجر الجوز ولا شو هاد؟
Is this a walnut tree or what is it?
إي هي شجرة جوز، هدول شجر جوز هدول.
Yes, this is a walnut tree, these are walnut trees.
نعم.
Yes.
هداك التوت العليق ليكه.
That's the blackberry bush over there.
واضح إي.
It's clear, yes.
التوت البري، كل الوادي تقريبا موجود.
Wild berries, they are present almost all over the valley.
وين في مي بموجود التوت.
Wherever there is water, the berries are present.
بظن هي النبعة واضحة أمامنا.
I think this spring is clear in front of us.
إي هي المي واضحة، أيوة، هي النبعة اللي جاية من كفر جنة هي.
Yes, the water is clear, exactly, this is the spring coming
from Kafr Jannah.
مو نبعة قريتنا هي.
It's not our village's spring.
نعم، واللي بتكمل عند هديك النبعة.
Yes, and which continues to that spring.
بالضبط أيوة، اللي بتكمل عهديك النبعة.
Exactly yes, which continues to that spring.
طبعا في جنب هي النبعة اللي جاية من كفر جنة، في نبعة جنبها
كمان.
Of course, next to this spring coming from Kafr Jannah,
there is another spring next to it.
في نبعة هون بالصخر كانت، هي ما بتطلع إلا أيام الأمطار
الغزيرة بس.
There was a spring here in the rock, it only flows during
days of heavy rain.
نعم، خلينا نوصل لعند النبعة ونحكي هنيك.
Yes, let's reach the spring and talk there.
ننزل شوي باتجاه النبعة.
Let's go down a bit towards the spring.
عم نشوف عن قرب.
We are looking closely.
واضح مجرى المي من هون مختار؟
Is the water course clear from here, Mukhtar?
إي جاي من هنيك.
Yes, it's coming from there.
صوت المي واضح.
The sound of water is clear.
نعم.
Yes.
في صعوبة والمنطقة وعرة.
There is difficulty and the area is rugged.
إي.
Yes.
نعم.
طبعا المي هلا ما هي نقية مثل أولي.
Of course, the water now is not as pure as before.
بسبب مياه الصرف الصحي وهي عم تنتقل ع المي يعني.
Because of wastewater and it's leaking into the water.
لأنه في تسريب للصرف الصحي عليها.
Because there is a leakage of sewage into it.
إي بالتسريب الصرف الصحي، ع المي.
Yes, sewage leaking into the water.
لكن واضح مجرى المي من هون.
But the water course is clear from here.
وكيف بتتجه نحو الغرب.
And how it flows towards the west.
الغرب الجنوبي.
South-west.
كان المجرى غزير يعني، كان كبير يعني.
The flow was abundant, it was large.
هيك هلا رح يصب بنهر عفرين؟
So will it flow into the Afrin River now?
لا نهر عفرين، لا نهر عفرين.
To the Afrin River, yes to the Afrin River.
بأي قرية بصب؟
In which village does it pour?
والله بيطلع من هون من عند قسطل كشك وما قسطل كشك وبينزل.
Well, it comes out from here by Qastal Keshk and Qastal
Keshk area and goes down.
تمام.
Alright.
وهذا التوت؟
And this mulberry?
نعم هذا التين.
Yes, this is a fig tree.
هذا.. هذا مو تين، نحن هاد.. هاد نوعية نحن بنقول له تيب.
This... this isn't a fig, this... this is a type we call
Teeb.
تيب؟
Teeb?
التيب أيوة.
Teeb, yes.
هاد يعني ذكر التين؟
Does this mean male fig?
أيوة هذا ذكر التين تقريبا.
Yes, this is approximately the male fig.
هاد نحن عنا أكلة مشهورة بيعملوا فيه.
We have a famous dish made with it.
بيجيبوا الحليب، وبيجيبوا هالتيب هاد بيطلع منه حليب.
They bring milk, and they bring this Teeb, from which a
milky sap comes out.
بيخلطوه هيك مع الحليب، بتصير متل القشطة يعني متل ال..
They mix it like this with the milk, and it becomes like
cream, like the...
متل الخميرة هاد؟
Like yeast, this?
مثل الخميرة أيوة.
Like yeast, yes.
بتصير مثل الزبدة، الحليب بصير مثل الزبدة يعني.
It becomes like butter, the milk becomes like butter.
طعمه لذيذ جدا جدا.
Its taste is very, very delicious.
هلا هون هي المنطقة كانت سياحية بس لا ما ننسى.
Now, this area used to be a tourist spot, we shouldn't
forget.
إنه هون كانت وجهة السياح اللي.. أو أهل حلب.. محافظة حلب..
That this was a destination for tourists who... or the
people of Aleppo... the Aleppo governorate...
مثل ما إنت ذكرت أنه أرمن وغير أرمن كانوا يجوا يوم الأحد.
As you mentioned that Armenians and non-Armenians used to
come on Sundays.
يوم الجمعة أخوتنا الإسلام كانوا يجوا، يوم الأحد أخوتنا
الأرمن كانوا يجوا.
On Friday, our Muslim brothers would come, on Sunday our
Armenian brothers would come.
المنطقة كلها مشجرة.
The whole area was forested.
كلها مشجرة هي كلها غزيرة يعني أشجار غزيرة جدا.
It was all forested, this whole area was dense, very dense
trees.
ومياه نقية وما كنت تشوف الشمس هون كلياتها يعني.
And pure water, and you couldn't see the sun here at all.
يعني هي المنطقة هون هلا عند النبعة تحت هي كلها كان فيها
أشجار يعني.
I mean this area here now, by the spring below, this all had
trees in it.
مختار خلينا نروح نكسب الوقت ونروح باتجاه زيارة حنان.
Mukhtar, let's go, save time and head towards the shrine of
Hannan.
ماشي ماشي.
Alright, alright.
تفضل.
Go ahead.
يلا.
Let's go.
هي هون نحن هلا نازلين على مقبرة مشعلة وزيارة حنان.
We are now going down to the Mash'alah cemetery and the
shrine of Hannan.
هي أكبر مقبرة تقريبا في منطقة عفرين.
This is probably the largest cemetery in the Afrin region.
وفي هون زيارة حنان، زيارة قديمة كمان.
And there is the shrine of Hannan here, an old shrine too.
وجامع حاليا مرمم من جديد، ورح نشوف هلا معالم الجامع ونحكي
شوي عن الجامع.
And a mosque that has recently been restored, and we will
now see the features of the mosque and talk a little about
it.
حسب ما فهمت مختار بأنه المقبرة يعني فيها قبور لمعظم أهالي
منطقة عفرين.
From what I understand, Mukhtar, the cemetery has graves for
most of the people of the Afrin region.
بالضبط بالضبط.
Exactly, exactly.
هي أغلب منطقة عفرين بيجوا بيدفنوا موتاهم هون.
Most of the Afrin region come and bury their dead here.
ظنا منهم إنه هون منطقة مباركة يعني.
Believing that this is a blessed area.
إنه حنان رجل مبارك، أو زيارة شغلة مباركة، فأغلب الناس بتيجي
بتدفن موتاها هون.
That Hannan was a blessed man, or the shrine is a blessed
thing, so most people come to bury their dead here.
وهذا هو مجرى المائي.
And this is the water course.
وهذا مجرى المائي، أيوة.
And this is the water course, yes.
هذا بيروح باتجاه عفرين، هذا بيجي من نبعة من كفر جنة، وبيجي
بنبعة مشعلة كان وبيصب بنهر عفرين.
This goes towards Afrin, it comes from a spring in Kafr
Jannah, and it used to flow into the Mash'alah spring and
pour into the Afrin River.
اللي شايفينه الآن هذا، هذا هو مزار حنان ولا شو هذا؟
What we are seeing now, is this the shrine of Hannan or what
is this?
لا هذا مقام قديم هذا بيقولوا له بير جعفر.
No, this is an old shrine, they call it Pir Ja'far.
مقام إيزيدي على حسب المعلومات التاريخية يعني.
A Yazidi shrine according to historical information.
إيزيدي؟
Yazidi?
إيزيدي أيوة.
Yazidi, yes.
بس ما في شي مؤكد يعني، هذا قول شعبي يعني.
But there is nothing certain, this is a popular saying.
بس مو مقام إسلامي يعني.
But it is not an Islamic shrine.
لأنه كانوا يتراودوا عليه أخوتنا الإيزيديين أيام أعيادهم
يعني.
Because our Yazidi brothers used to frequent it during their
holidays.
نعم.
Yes.
وهي المقبرة هي نحن هلا رايحين باتجاه الزيارة.
And this cemetery, we are now heading towards the shrine.
مقبرة زيارة حنان.
The cemetery of the shrine of Hannan.
زيارة حنان، أيوا.
The shrine of Hannan, yes.
مشهورة يعني كتير بمنطقة عفرين على أنها مقصد سياحي.
It's very famous in the Afrin region as a tourist
destination.
مقصود.. أيوة مقصد سياحي، ويقال يعني حسب الأقوال الشعبية طبعا
ما في مسند تاريخي.
A destination... yes, a tourist destination, and it is said
according to popular sayings, of course there is no
historical evidence.
يقال إنه هذا يوحنا المعمدان، هيك يقولوا القدامى الختيارية.
It is said that this is John the Baptist, that's what the
old elders say.
بس مسند تاريخي ما في.
But there is no historical proof.
إنه هون.. إنه هون يعني قبر يوحنا المعمدان؟
That here... that here is the tomb of John the Baptist?
أيوة إنه هون قبر يوحنا المعمدان.
Yes, that the tomb of John the Baptist is here.
فالإسلام ساووه حنان، حنان صار يوحنا حنان.
So Muslims called him Hannan, Hannan, Yohanna became Hannan.
فهيك يقال يعني، بس ما في مسند تاريخي، يعني كتاب أو شي يثبت
هالشيء هذا.
So it is said, but there is no historical evidence, like a
book or something to prove this.
هدول أجدادنا كانوا يحكوا هالحكي هذا، بس ما في مسند تاريخي
يعني كتاب أو شي يثبت هالشي هذا.
Our ancestors used to say this, but there is no historical
proof, I mean a book or something to prove this.
الآن نحن وصلنا للـ..
Now we have reached the...
يعني هلا وصلنا لزيارة حنان.
I mean, now we have reached the shrine of Hannan.
رح ندخل للداخل هلا كمان.
We will go inside now as well.
لحظة.
A moment.
تفضل.
Go ahead.
يا الله.
Oh God.
هي هون الزيارة مختار؟
Is this the shrine here, Mukhtar?
إي هي الزيارة، وهذا باب الزيارة هلا رح ندخل عالزيارة.
Yes, this is the shrine, and this is the door of the shrine,
we will now enter the shrine.
وهي القبور هي كلياتها مبينة من هون كمان.
And these graves, they are all visible from here too.
يعني مساحة القبور شاسعة جدا يعني.
I mean, the area of the graves is very vast.
قلت لك يعني الناس بتتبرك بهالمنطقة هي وبيجوا أغلبهم أغلب
الضيع اللي حوالينا بيدفنوا موتاهم هون.
I told you, people seek blessings in this area and most of
them, most of the villages around us bury their dead here.
وطبعا بالإضافة لقبور أهل مشعلة الأصليين كمان كلها موجودة
هون.
And of course, in addition to the graves of the original
people of Mash'alah, they are all here too.
شرط..
Condition...
وهي نحن هلا حاليا رح ندخل هون عالجامع.
And we are currently going to enter the mosque here.
هي هون هي زيارة حنان؟
Is this here the shrine of Hannan?
يعني هذا يعتبر معلم تاريخي.
I mean, this is considered a historical monument.
إي شو كان يصير هون قبل.. قبل ما نحكي في التاريخ، إي شو كان
يصير هون في الأعياد؟
Yeah, what used to happen here before... before we talk
about history, yeah what used to happen here during the
holidays?
كان وجهة سياحية، كان يجي هون..
It was a tourist destination, people used to come here...
هون وجهة سياحية كبيرة يعني أيام عيد الفطر وأيام عيد الأضحى.
Here was a major tourist destination during Eid al-Fitr and
Eid al-Adha.
نظرا لوجود أغلب قبور المنطقة هون كلياته فيها.
Given the presence of most of the region's graves here in
it.
فيجوا من الساعة وحدة ثنتين وجه الصبح، يزوروا قبور ميتينهم
واشلون؟
So they would come from one or two in the morning, visit the
graves of their dead, you see?
ويصلوا هون، صلاة العيد..
And pray here, the Eid prayer...
...camiya, û... û dibe vir cemaat, eydan ji zarokan re, dibe
bestat û ma bestat yanî çawa.
...the mosque, and... and gatherings happen here, Eids for
the kids, there are stands and such, you know.
Ey kano hon... yidbahû ndûra...
Yes, they used to here... slaughter their vows...
Kano yidbahû ndûra? El-Îslam yanî exleb el-Îslam kano yîcû
yidbahû ndûra hon, hon şlon?
They used to slaughter vows? Muslims, meaning mostly Muslims
would come to slaughter vows here, how so?
Eş fî ilhun nedir aw şexle, yîcû yidbahû...
Whatever vow or thing they had, they would come and
slaughter...
Hel hesb ma fhimt inno b-hal meqbera fî qubûr wesaniyye, wa
qubûr uxra eşo fî?
As I understood, in this cemetery there are pagan graves,
and other graves, what is there?
Êh fî hon... fî asar la-qubûr yahûdiyye, wa qubûr mesîhiyye,
wa qubûr wesaniyye, û axir tişt qubûr îslamiyye.
Yes, here there are... traces of Jewish graves, Christian
graves, pagan graves, and lastly Islamic graves.
Yanî el-meqbere yu'taqad inna qedîme cidden cidden.
Meaning the cemetery is believed to be very very old.
Lîenno el-mintaqa kigul hiye mintaqa fîha asar romaniyye, û
ma qabil er-romaniyye, û bîzantiyye...
Because the area in general is an area with Roman ruins,
pre-Roman, and Byzantine...
Biz-zabt, biz-zabt... wusûlen li-ahd el-îslamî...
Exactly, exactly... up to the Islamic era...
Biz-zabt, wusûlen li-ahd el-îslamî. Xelîna xelîna nşûf el-
mekan hon... yalla... tefaddal.
Exactly, up to the Islamic era. Let's let's see the place
here... let's go... go ahead.
Yanî ev meqam pir qedîm e, yanî çawa.
So this shrine is very old, you know.
N'am. Fî hon hellaq fî darîh hon...
Yes. Now there is a shrine here...
Darîh, eyy huwwe nefsû l-î am nihkî anhu... darîh Hennan...
yqal inno darîh Hennan yanî şlon.
A shrine, yes, the same one we are talking about... the
shrine of Hannan... it's said it's the shrine of Hannan, you
know.
El-lî huwwe...
The one who...
El-lî inzeker b-kutub et-tarîx inno qed yekûn Yuhanna, aw
qed yekûn... ahad cunûd... Dawûd aleyhisselam...
The one mentioned in history books, that it might be
Yohanna, or might be... one of the soldiers of... David,
peace be upon him...
...yani yqal inno huwwe hon madfûn. Hon el-qubûr...
...meaning it is said he is buried here. Here are the
graves...
Ev e darîh.
This is the shrine.
Eywe ev e darîh.
Yes, this is the shrine.
Ev qedîm e cidden hon.
This is very old here.
Ev qedîm ktîr qed yekûn eqdem min el-bîna...
This is very old, it might be older than the building...
Qed yekûn eqdem min el-bîna, temam... Û ev qebir, ev çi ye?
It might be older than the building, right... And this
grave, what is this?
Û ev kaman qebir e... û hon kaman qebir bes ma yî ma'rûfe
yanî hiyye qubûr lamîn ma hada bya'rif yanî.
And this is also a grave... and here is a grave too, but
it's not known, meaning whose graves they are, nobody knows.
Bes ev yê ku meşhûr e, ziyareta Hennan, bi navê wî ye, ew
Hennan e.
But this one that is famous, the shrine of Hannan, in his
name, is Hannan.
Yqal inno Yuhanna el-Ma'medan, ahad telamîz... Seydîna el-
Mesîh.
It is said he is John the Baptist, one of the disciples
of... our Lord Christ.
Yqal huwwe ahad cunûd... Seydîna Dawûd aleyhisselam...
It is said he is one of the soldiers of... our Lord David,
peace be upon him...
...bil ma'reke... istişhed û îcû defenûh hon.
...in battle... was martyred and they came and buried him
here.
Fe ma'lûmat tarîxiyye mu'ekkede ma fî yanî. Hay yqal ala
lisan... ecdadna.
So there is no confirmed historical information. This is
said by the tongues of... our ancestors.
Wa qed yekûn metel ma inno mahtût aleyh... şu mahtût aleyh
hon?
And it might be like what is written on it... what is
written on it here?
B-kil el-ahwal... yani fî ayat quraniyye... fî ayat
quraniyye eyywe.
In any case... meaning there are Quranic verses... there are
Quranic verses, yes.
Xelîna nşûf hellaq hon el-bîna... tefaddal.
Let's see the building now here... go ahead.
Ev bîna qeddeş umrû... mixtar?
How old is this building... Mukhtar?
Wallah ev bîna ktîr qedîm... yanî ktîr ktîr qedîm yanî.
By God this building is very old... meaning very very old.
El-lawha hon mektûb aleyha...
The plaque here has written on it...
Hay el-lawha hay mektûb aleyha inno teremmeme el-mescid ala
dor es-Sultan Ebdilhemîd...
This plaque here has written on it that the mosque was
restored during the era of Sultan Abdul Hamid...
...Wali Heleb... Huseyîn Cemîl Paşa... huwwe lî remmemû.
...the Wali of Aleppo... Hussein Jamil Pasha... he is the
one who restored it.
Fî am 1303 hicrî...
In the year 1303 Hijri...
Eywa... ma'naha huwwe kan mewcûd qabil el-1303.
Yes... meaning it existed before 1303.
Ekîd ekîd...
Sure, sure...
Lîenno hay el-awamîd... saraha hay el-awamîd qedîme ktîr.
Because these columns... honestly these columns are very
old.
Qedîme cidden... Hay te'ûd lil-ahd er-romanî aw meqabir er-
roman...
Very old... This goes back to the Roman era or Roman
graves...
Yanî hay wada'û el-esasî lal-cami', yanî şlon.
So this is its main foundation for the mosque, you see.
Hay bit-termîma el-axîra... hay termemet ala hal-esas...
This with the last restoration... it was restored on this
foundation...
Kano fî şexlat muxfiyye killa ezhirûha yanî, el-bîna el-
qedîm reccaûh ala ahdû el-qedîm yanî.
There were hidden things they revealed all of them, the old
building they returned it to its old era.
Hetta el-mekan barid hon ktîr. Û barra el-cew har,
Even the place is very cold here. And outside the weather is
hot,
...ev ye'kis inno fî semake bis-seqef... û fî semake bil-
hîtan ktîr kaman... yanî bîna' ktîr qedîm.
...this reflects that there is thickness in the roof... and
a lot of thickness in the walls too... meaning a very old
building.
Huwwe tuhfe heqîqeten tuhfe hay.
It is a masterpiece, truly a masterpiece.
Mirov texmîn nake eger... bimeşe qurbû, aw a-tarîq el-reîsî
inno fî... me'lem siyahî qedîm.
One wouldn't guess if... walking near it, or on the main
road, that there is... an old tourist landmark.
Min zeman el-alem kanit tîcî tzûrû...
Since a long time ago people used to come visit it...
Min kil el-amakin?
From everywhere?
Min kil el-amakin, hetta min Eş-Şam kano yîcû, min Heleb...
yanî huwwe me'lem tarîxî yanî... û siyahî.
From everywhere, even from Damascus they would come, from
Aleppo... meaning it is a historical landmark... and
tourist.
Û ev e şeklê wî... eywa... ev e şeklê wî yê esasî.
And this is its shape... yes... this is its main shape.
Teşekkur mixtar...
Thank you Mukhtar...
Ala rasî, Ehla wa sehlen...
You're welcome, welcome...
Ellah ya'tîk el-afiye... şukran îlek... ya ehla wa sehlen.
May God give you health... thank you... welcome.
Selam aleykum.
Peace be upon you.
Wa aleykum selam... Ellah ya'tîkum el-afiye... Ahlen wa
sehlen.
Peace be upon you too... May God give you health... Welcome.
Întû min sukkan el-muxeyem?
Are you from the residents of the camp?
E n'am min sukkan el-muxeyem.
Yes, from the residents of the camp.
Min wên?
Where from?
Şeref la-hon şway... Wallah nihne min Rif Heleb el-Xerbî.
Come closer a bit here... By God we are from the western
countryside of Aleppo.
Û hecî?
And the Hajji?
Û el-hecî kaman nefis eş-şî...
And the Hajji is also the same thing...
Ma Anadan.
With Anadan.
Anadan.
Ahlen wa sehlen bîkum... Rif xerbî û şemalî...
Welcome to you... Western and northern countryside...
Ehlen weshlen bîk, ala rasî.
Welcome to you, you're welcome.
Hkûlî an wade'kum hon... şlon wade' hal-muxeyem?
Tell me about your situation here... how is the situation of
this camp?
Wallah hellaq fî... wa nihne bi-mûcib remezan... el-wade'
el-maîşî hon wallahî sa'ib şway.
By God now there is... and due to Ramadan... the living
situation here by God is a bit difficult.
Lîenno... munazzemat ma aadet tsai'd hal-alem.
Because... organizations no longer help these people.
Wa şofet aynak ed-dinya şob... yanî hellaq xiyam... nar ma
byinbirik fîha...
And as you see the weather is hot... meaning now these
tents... are fire, you can't sit in them...
El-alem fî han-nehar... am tidrub tibrik şway taht eş-şecer,
lî enno... şob, derecet el-herare... ma btinwisif.
The people during the day... go to sit a bit under the
trees, because... it's hot, the temperature... cannot be
described.
Kam aîle hon fî?
How many families are here?
Teqrîben hon şî mîye û saba'taşar aîle.
Approximately here there are some 117 families.
Mîye û saba'taşar aîle... Eş byiştiğlû bil-umum?
117 families... What do they work in generally?
Wallah hinne bil-umum kanû... yanî bil-xerbî kanû yiştiğlû
bil-hacer û masalih.
By God generally they used to... meaning in the west they
worked in stone and trades.
Hellaq el-lî indû şexle amla hon... haliyen wallah haliyen
el-alem killeha barke...
Now whoever has a job does it here... currently by God
currently all the people are sitting...
...min dûn şixil min dûn şî... lî enno ma fî masalih... ma
fî şixil hon...
...without work without anything... because there are no
trades... there is no work here...
...werşat, şexlat, inno el-alem tiştexil, ma fî. Eş-şebab
haliyen wallah, tis'în bil mîye barkîn... min dûn amal.
...workshops, jobs, for people to work, there isn't. The
youth currently by God, ninety percent are sitting...
without work.
Hecî hkî lî ank... hkî lî an aîltak.
Hajji tell me about yourself... tell me about your family.
Nefis eş-şî... yanî cîna barekna hon... sarlna sine û
şahrayn... b-hal... muxeyem.
The same thing... meaning we came and sat here... it's been
a year and two months... in this... camp.
El-hemdulillah... eş bedna nsawî hêk... Ellah keteb.
Praise be to God... what can we do... God destined it.
Şo kint tiştexil?
What did you use to work in?
Ana kint muwezzef... tala't a't-teqa'ud û barakt. Ma fî şî.
I was an employee... I retired and sat. There is nothing.
Wuladak eş byiştiğlû?
What do your children work in?
Ma byiştiğlû fî şî... tawil... îndî ibin istaz, am
bihawil... yerûh û yicî hetta... yidarris.
They don't work in anything... at all... I have a son who is
a teacher, he is trying... to go and come to... teach.
Û îndî wahid... bil-bekalorya, hal-sine.
And I have one... in high school, this year.
Teyyib, qeddeş nisbet el-lî byiştexlû hon fil-muxeyem?
Okay, what is the percentage of those who work here in the
camp?
Daîfe ktîr, ma fî... yanî aşra bil-mîye... teqrîben şî aşra
bil-mîye.
Very weak, there isn't... meaning ten percent...
approximately some ten percent.
Aşra bil-mîye.
Ten percent.
Ala qetkum ma ehl ed-day'e... ehl Meş'ele, şlon?
Your relationship with the people of the village... the
people of Mashaalah, how is it?
Kweyîse, el-hemdulillah. Eş-şebab killhum... kweyîsîn... ehl
ed-day'e yanî... ma bîqessirû.
Good, praise be to God. The youth all of them... are good...
the people of the village I mean... they don't fall short.
Fî medrese?
Is there a school?
Fî lekan fî medrese... fî medrese Meş'ele hon qerîbe hon.
el-etfal am trûh.
There is, of course there is a school... there is the
Mashaalah school near here. The children are going.
Yani wuladkum am trûh a-medrese?
Meaning your children are going to school?
Am trûh eyy... fî nisbet etfal yani kweyise am trûh
a-medrese.
They are going yes... there is a good percentage of children
going to school.
Û bi-mûcib ehl ed-day'e el-ekrad hon... nehne ahl yanî
bininzil binrûh, bincî înd ba'dna.
And regarding the people of the village, the Kurds here...
we are family I mean we go down, we go and come to each
other.
El-hemdulillah rebbil alemîn... es-sile kweyîse el-
hemdulillah rebbil alemîn.
Praise be to the Lord of the worlds... the connection is
good, praise be to the Lord of the worlds.
Îndî kaman bil-camî fî helqet etfal ana bedarris fîha fil-
camî... el-hemdulillah.
I also have in the mosque a children's circle that I teach
in the mosque... praise be to God.
Kam tifl îndak?
How many children do you have?
Fî... yani îndna nihne tlet heleqat... kil wahde... kil şeb
şî işrîn talib. Wa fî talibat kaman... anîsat biderrisû.
There are... I mean we have three circles... each one...
each young man has some twenty students. And there are
female students too... female teachers are teaching.
Maşallah.
Mashallah.
Yani am nihawil el-hemdulillah... inno Ellah hêk...
yihelî... ma steta'na fî binkaddim.
I mean we are trying praise be to God... that God like
this... enables us... as much as we can we offer.
Ellah ya'tîkum el-afiye û yiczîkum el-xeyr.
May God give you health and reward you with good.
Ahlen wa sehlen... Ellah ysalmek.
Welcome... May God keep you safe.
Bedna nşûf aîle... û nimşî.
We want to see a family... and go.
Ellah ya'tîkum el-afiye... selam aleykum.
May God give you health... peace be upon you.
Selam werahmetullah...
Peace and mercy of God...
Şlonêk?
How are you?
Eşû ismik întî?
What is your name?
Nûr.
Nour.
Ehley ya Nûr, wên bêtkum?
Welcome Nour, where is your house?
Hon.
Here.
Hon?
Here?
Selam aleykum... Merheba ya hecce şlonkun?
Peace be upon you... Hello Hajja, how are you?
El-hemdulillah...
Praise be to God...
Şlonkun antum... şlon sihhetkun...
How are you all... how is your health...
El-hemdulillah rebbil alemin...
Praise be to the Lord of the worlds...
Min wên intû?
Where are you from?
Nihne min Rif Heleb el-Xerbî.
We are from the western countryside of Aleppo.
Û hecce?
And the Hajja?
Qitlek kaman min Rif Heleb el-Xerbî...
I told you also from the western countryside of Aleppo...
Intû cîran hon?
Are you neighbors here?
Eywe... yanî nihne wulad amm...
Yes... I mean we are cousins...
Yani mu'zam el-alem e-lî hon min... nefis el-minteqa.
Meaning most of the people who are here are from... the same
area.
Ey min el-mintaqa el-xerbiye... bas nihne axir şî... yanî
sarlna sine û şahrayn tlete hêk...
Yes from the western area... but we were the last thing...
meaning it's been a year and two three months like this...
Yani dirne... ma laqayna metrah nibrik fî... cîna lehon
Ellah be'atna d-hal-metrah, ta'awayna fî waberekna...
Meaning we wandered... we couldn't find a place to sit in...
we came here God sent us to this place, we took shelter in
it and sat...
Hon hellaq sar bedal betna yanî... bêtena rah lîenno birik
fî el-ceyş... îza sarlak xabar... tab'an sadîqî...
Here now it became instead of our house I mean... our house
is gone because the army sat in it... if you heard the
news... of course my friend...
Ey el-hemdulillah, a-kil hal...
Yes praise be to God, in any case...
Yani, ala hal-hal... wal maîşe hon sa'be wa dayqa ktîr...
yani... bita'anî ktîr.
Meaning, in this situation... and the living here is hard
and very tight... meaning... you suffer a lot.
Kil nehar mnita'zzeb û el-xeyme şob, wa ma fî mirweha, wa la
fî şî... wil muxeyem... aatşîn berkefî...
Every day we suffer and the tent is hot, and there is no
fan, and there is nothing... and the camp... is thirsty
maybe...
Eşu hal... kîf teqdû yomkum fî remezan?
What is the situation... how do you spend your day in
Ramadan?
Tefaddalî... xelîne nihkî me'ik şway kaman, şerefî.
Go ahead... let's talk with you a bit too, come here.
Wallah min qaddî bil... yani b-remezan inno bi-tiştehî tnamî
şway fin-nehar...
By God we spend it in... meaning in Ramadan that you desire
to sleep a bit during the day...
...ma btehsinî, wil merdan wa ma'zûr. Ena merîda sahebt îndî
kelawî.
...you can't, and the sick and excused. I am sick, I have
kidneys.
Biştehî axemmid şiqqa fin-nehar, am bawessil lil-mesa nêzze
kome.
I desire to close my eyes a bit during the day, I reach the
evening dripping like a pile.
Bimruq, bihut rasî wa bnam ba'd el-iftar. Ma bahsin eûd
basha a-halî tawil.
I go in, put my head down and sleep after Iftar. I can't
wake up to myself at all anymore.
Selametkun, ma fî mu'assasa bo may?
Your safety, isn't there a facility for water?
Ma ba'rif, fî, ma fî xeyr rebbil alemîn, yetwella el-emir,
wa yiddexxel fî hal-emir... wa hal hkaye wa haş-şexle.
I don't know, there is, there is no one but the Lord of the
worlds, to take charge of the matter, and intervene in this
matter... and this story and this thing.
Wal qalb el-xeyme mitl en-nar... hellaq qa'dîn fîha bas mitl
nar el-hamra... mitl tenceret el-buxar...
And the heart of the tent is like fire... now sitting in it
but like red fire... like a pressure cooker...
...btiftil eyam tenceret el-buxar... İze... nar, nar hemra.
...it turns days into a pressure cooker... If... fire, red
fire.
Yekûn Ellah yib'atilna... şiqfet mirweha... şiqfet
bettariyye... şiqfet şî hêk...
May God send us... a piece of a fan... a piece of a
battery... a piece of something like that...
...inno la-ihtiyacat hal-xeyme... yani, btibrik şway fîl
xeyme... ma bnihsin...
...that for the needs of this tent... meaning, you sit a bit
in the tent... we can't...
...nidell faytîn tali'în, qaidîn baqa... yani, el-mesa a-l-
brûde şway, bnidwax sifar...
...we keep going in and out, sitting then... meaning, in the
evening in the coolness a bit, we get dizzy to zero...
Xelîne nis'al el-um hon... Um... eş hadirtik?
Let's ask the mother here... Mother... what is your name?
Um Midyen.
Um Midyan.
Um Midyen... hkî lî hon xedamat el-may... xedamat el-
xubiz... fî kehreba... şlon el-weda hon?
Um Midyan... tell me here about the water services... bread
services... is there electricity... how is the situation
here?
Ma fî kehreba... Wallahî el-weda... yani sa'b.
There is no electricity... By God the situation... meaning
difficult.
El-may fî may bas ekter el-ahyan... yani qalîl el-may aleyna
wa ma bitkeffî...
Water, there is water but most of the times... meaning water
is little on us and it doesn't suffice...
...el-alem killeha... yani yom b-yom, la-ycîbû lna may, û ma
bitkeffîna.
...all the people... meaning day by day, they bring us
water, and it doesn't suffice us.
Wal ihtiyacat el-xubiz kaman... kaman el-xubiz, welleh
qeta'û anna...
And the bread needs too... also the bread, by God they cut
it from us...
عادي كويس كتير، مثلاً شهر رمضان، هلق ما في أكوس منه، شهر
الخير، يعني ما في هالدعم الكويس فيه، ما في هلق يعني تقصير
كتير بهالشهر هاد.
It is very good, for example, the month of Ramadan, there is
nothing better than it now, the month of goodness, but there
isn't much good support in it, I mean there's a lot of
shortcoming now, in this month.
بنتمنى منكم ومن كل إنسان بشوفنا وبساعد البشر، يعني هالعالم
اللي فقيرة، نحن هون نازحين. كل من واحد بيساعد لو كان في شربة
مي الله بناله قصر في الجنة.
We hope from you, and from every person who sees us and
helps people, I mean these poor people, we are displaced
here. Whoever helps, even with a sip of water, God will
build them a palace in heaven.
إي نحن بنتمنى منكم ومن كل إنسان بحب يساعدنا، بنشكره وبنشكر
كل إنسان بيساعد وبنقول له هو كمان الله يرفع البلا عنه، وإن
شاء الله تعالى بيجعلهم من الأتقياء الصالحين.
Yes, we hope from you and from every person who loves to
help us, we thank him and we thank every person who helps,
and we tell him may God lift the affliction from him too,
and God Almighty make them among the righteous and pious.
إن شاء الله، إن شاء الله. نحن إعلام، نحن إن شاء الله وظيفتنا
إنه يعني نسلط الضوء على وضعكم.
God willing, God willing. We are media, our job, God
willing, is to shed light on your situation.
وإن شاء الله بيشوفوكم جهات معنية، مجالس ومنظمات وإن شاء الله
ما بينسوكم. الله يعطيكم العافية، شكراً إلكن.
And hopefully, concerned authorities, councils, and
organizations will see you and, God willing, they won't
forget you. May God give you health, thank you.
كتر خيركم.
May God increase your goodness.
الله يسلمكم، السلام عليكم. هذا واجبنا يا أمي.
May God keep you safe, peace be upon you. This is our duty,
mother.
الله يسلمكم، كتر خيركم، سلم دياتكم.
May God keep you safe, may God increase your goodness, bless
your hands.
السلام عليكم.
Peace be upon you.
وعليكم السلام ورحمة الله.
And peace and mercy of God be upon you.
الله يعطيك العافية. نتعرف عليك؟
May God give you health. May we know you?
أبو رحيم الشامي، من قرية التل في ريف دمشق.
Abu Raheem Al-Shami, from the village of Al-Tall in the
Damascus countryside.
أهلاً وسهلاً. ساكن هون؟
Welcome. Do you live here?
نعم، في قرية مشعلة.
Yes, in the village of Mash'alah.
شو بتشتغل؟
What do you work as?
فلاح وإمام مسجد.
A farmer and a mosque imam.
يا أهلاً وسهلاً فيك، أصبحت خبير بطباع الناس هون، احكيلنا عن
طباع الناس هون. أهل مشعلة شلونهم؟
You are very welcome. You have become an expert on the
nature of the people here, tell us about the nature of the
people here. How are the people of Mash'alah?
نعم، أهل مشعلة هم أهل أناس طيبين جداً، إن كان من الكرد ومن
العرب.
Yes, the people of Mash'alah are very good people, whether
they are Kurds or Arabs.
منسجمين جداً، مجتمعين مع بعضهم البعض، تتخلل هذه المحبة أو
الأخوة، متآلفة بينهم.
Very harmonious, gathered with each other, permeated by this
love or brotherhood, familiar with each other.
يجتمعون في بيت الله عز وجل، ويتفرقون في أشغالهم وفي أعمالهم.
هذه من أساساتهم يعني.
They gather in the house of God Almighty, and they disperse
to their jobs and their work. This is one of their
foundations, I mean.
تمام، هنن بسيطين، صعبين، سهلين شلونهم؟
Great, are they simple, difficult, easy-going? How are they?
بسيطين جداً، روحهم كروح الأرض.
Very simple, their soul is like the soul of the land.
يا سلام عالتعبير الحلو.
Wow, what a beautiful expression.
وروح الشجر والمي الحلوة اللي عندهم. زيتونهم، زيتونهم وأرضهم
الخضراء.
And the soul of the trees and the sweet water they have.
Their olives, their olives and their green land.
تبعث فيهم روح المحبة والألفة والإخاء، وعلمتنا منهم دروس
شديدة جداً.
It sends into them the spirit of love, familiarity, and
brotherhood, and we learned very profound lessons from them.
شو تعلمتوا منهم؟
What did you learn from them?
تعلمنا منهم حب الأرض، وتعلمنا منهم الصبر والجلد.
We learned from them the love of the land, and we learned
from them patience and endurance.
ترى ختيار عمره 90 سنة، وهو يفلح في الأرض وهو يرعى هذا الشجر
ويرعى هذا الثمر.
You see an old man who is 90 years old, and he is plowing
the land, and he is taking care of these trees and taking
care of these fruits.
كلام جميل. اللباس اللي لابسه، من شغل مشعلة ولا جايبه من غير
مكان؟
Beautiful words. The clothes you are wearing, are they from
Mash'alah's work or did you bring them from somewhere else?
نعم، من شغل القرية هون.
Yes, from the village's work here.
شلون الأسعار هون بالمناسبة؟
By the way, how are the prices here?
الأسعار جيدة جداً.
The prices are very good.
كويسة؟
Are they good?
نعم، رخيصة، وفي متناول الأيدي.
Yes, cheap, and affordable.
الله يعطيك العافية يا شيخي.
May God give you health, my Sheikh.
أهلاً وسهلاً حياكم الله جميعاً.
Welcome, may God greet you all.
شكراً إلك، السلام عليكم.
Thank you, peace be upon you.
الله يكرمكم.
May God honor you.
خلينا ندخل على هالدكان. يا رب.
Let's enter this shop. Oh Lord.
السلام عليكم.
Peace be upon you.
وعليكم السلام ورحمة الله.
And peace and mercy of God be upon you.
الله يعطيكم العافية.
May God give you health.
أهلاً وسهلاً.
Welcome.
مرحبا أختي.
Hello, sister.
ما عم تحكي. السلام عليكم.
She's not talking. Peace be upon you.
وعليكم السلام ورحمة الله.
And peace and mercy of God be upon you.
شلونكم؟
How are you?
الحمد لله.
Praise be to God.
عمي حضرتك من هون؟
Uncle, are you from here?
إي من سكانها، من هون، أهلاً وسهلاً.
Yes, from its residents, from here, welcome.
تفضل ارتاح هون شوي خلينا نحكي.
Please, rest here a bit, let's talk.
إي تفضل.
Yes, go ahead.
احكيلي شلون الوضع هون، وضع الناس هون، الحالة الاقتصادية،
المعيشية، شلون؟
Tell me, how is the situation here, the situation of the
people here, the economic and living conditions, how are
they?
الوضع الحمد لله، يعني الوضع بشكل عام، ميسورة العالم يعني.
The situation, praise be to God, I mean the situation in
general, people are well-off, I mean.
ميسورة؟
Well-off?
ميسورة الحمد لله. يعني اللي عم يشتغل، اللي مثلاً عنده شي
شغلة مثلاً عم يضبطها.
Well-off, praise be to God. Meaning the one who is working,
the one who, for example, has some work he is managing.
اللي عنده أرض مثلاً هلق السكان الضيعة الأصليين، يعني الحمد
لله الأمور ماشية يعني.
The one who has land, for example, the original residents of
the village, I mean, praise be to God, things are going
well.
يعني متوسط الناس، أهالي القرية والمهجرين لهون، فيك تقول جيد،
وسط، ضعيف، شلون؟
So the average of the people, the people of the village and
the displaced people here, can you say good, medium, weak,
how is it?
هلق فيك تقول يعني وسطية، يعني وسطية، الأمور يعني شبه مقبولة
يعني.
Now, you can say, I mean, average, I mean average, things
are, I mean, somewhat acceptable.
شو بيشتغلوا معظمهم هون؟
What do most of them work in here?
والله بيشتغلوا كل واحد يعني إله شغل مثلاً معين بيشتغل فيه.
Well, they work, everyone, I mean, has a specific job they
work in.
في أغلبيتهم بيتاجروا مثلاً بشغلات، مثلاً بيشتروا وبيبيعوا
مثل سيارات مثلاً، أو هيك شغلات.
The majority of them trade, for example, in things, for
example, they buy and sell like cars, for example, or things
like that.
والزراعة؟
And agriculture?
والزراعة، الزراعة هلق لا، الزراعة هلق بس يعني السكان
الأصليين، يعني هنن اللي بيشتغلوا.
And agriculture, agriculture now, no, agriculture now is
just, I mean, the original residents, I mean, they are the
ones who work in it.
يعني زراعة وتربية الحيوانات. والمهجرين بيشتغلوا بالتجارة؟
Meaning agriculture and animal husbandry. And the displaced
people work in trade?
طبعاً بيشتغلوا بشكل عام يعني بالتجارة.
Of course, they work in general, I mean, in trade.
أنت من هون ولا من المهجرين؟
Are you from here or from the displaced?
لا أنا من سكانها.
No, I am from its residents.
يا أهلاً وسهلاً.
You are very welcome.
الله يسلمك.
May God keep you safe.
أعطيني عينة عن الأسعار.
Give me a sample of the prices.
والله الأسعار، يعني شبه مقبولة يعني حالياً بهالفترة.
Well, the prices, I mean, are somewhat acceptable, I mean,
currently in this period.
يعني مثلاً اعطيني شي. مثل البندورة.
I mean, for example, give me something. Like tomatoes.
هلق البندورة مثلاً عم نبيعها بـ 1700 عالسوري عم نبيعها.
Now, tomatoes, for example, we are selling them for 1700, in
Syrian (pounds) we are selling them.
والكوسا بـ 1500، الليمون بـ 2000.
And zucchini for 1500, lemons for 2000.
والتفاح بـ 1000، الأصفر والأحمر.
And apples for 1000, the yellow and the red.
البطاطا والخس؟
Potatoes and lettuce?
الخس يعني الكيلو بـ 500، البطاطا بـ 600. يعني أسعار شبه
مقبولة يعني.
Lettuce, I mean, a kilo is 500, potatoes are 600. I mean,
prices are somewhat acceptable.
اللي بيسألك، الناس بتاخد هون بالتقسيط ولا بالدين؟
One who asks you, do people buy here in installments or on
credit?
هلق في اللي حالته مثلاً درويش يعني ما عنده استطاعة.
Now, there are those whose situation, for example, is poor,
meaning they don't have the ability.
مثلاً الراتب للراتب، بياخدوا رواتب، بيدفعوا عالراتب مثلاً.
For example, from salary to salary, they take salaries, they
pay on the salary, for example.
وفي منهم أمورهم ماشية يعني، أمورهم ماشية تمام يعني ما
بياخدوا بالدين.
And there are some whose affairs are going well, I mean,
their affairs are going perfectly, I mean, they don't take
on credit.
يا سيدي الله يرزقكم، شو في هون من إنتاج الضيعة؟
My sir, may God provide for you, what is here from the
village's production?
والله من إنتاج الضيعة ما في.
Well, from the village's production, there isn't any.
أبداً؟ ألبان، أجبان ما عندكم؟
Never? Don't you have dairy, cheese?
لا من الضيعة ما في، عم يجي من برات الضيعة.
No, from the village there isn't any, it's coming from
outside the village.
هلق بنجيب من برات الضيعة، بس من قلب الضيعة ما في حالياً هلق.
Now we bring from outside the village, but from the heart of
the village there isn't any currently.
الله يعطيكم العافية.
May God give you health.
شكراً إلك.
Thank you.
مية سلامة، أهلاً وسهلاً.
A hundred welcomes, welcome.
خلص الوقت وخلصت الجولة وما خلصنا استكشاف وتنقيب عن الجمال.
The time is over and the tour is over, but we haven't
finished exploring and excavating the beauty.
بهالضيعة الصغيرة الحلوة، مشعلة، التابعة لناحية شران، منطقة
عفرين ريف حلب الشمالي.
In this beautiful little village, Mash'alah, belonging to
Sharran sub-district, Afrin region, northern Aleppo
countryside.
بدنا منكم تتفاعلوا معنا وتعطونا رأيكم بهالجولة.
We want you to interact with us and give us your opinion on
this tour.
ولمتابعة برنامجنا تابعوا صفحة الفيس الخاصة بالقناة.
And to follow our program, follow the channel's Facebook
page.
وأيضاً موقعنا على الإنترنت halabtodaytv.net.
And also our website halabtodaytv.net.
السلام عليكم ورحمة الله وبركاته.
Peace, mercy, and blessings of God be upon you.
[Muzîk]
[Music]